Guide to the Sheldon B. Sosna Papers, 1922-2001 and undated, bulk 1948-1991 RL.01233
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sheldon B. Sosna papers
1922-2005 and undated bulk 1948-1991
bulk
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sosna, Sheldon B.
RL.01233
8.6 Linear Feet
Retired advertising executive. Collection documents Sosna's long career as an advertising executive and consultant, and contains materials from a wide variety of formats, including correspondence, writings, printed material, advertisement proofs and clippings, sketches, scrapbooks, slides, negatives, and film. The collection primarily provides a record of advertising campaigns Sosna developed as a copy supervisor, creative director, and advertising executive at Gershuny Associates, Leo Burnett, Grant Advertising, Doherty Clifford Steers & Shenfield, Sullivan Stauffer Colwell & Bayles, Norman Craig & Kummel, and J.M. Mathes, from 1948 to 1973; the collection has limited material relating to the specific agencies for which he worked. In addition, the collection documents Sosna's later writings, lectures, and seminars as an independent consultant in retail and supermarket advertising from the 1970s through 2001, including a complete run of the Supermarket Advertising Newsletter (1981-2000) and a copy of his book Dodge #9: How to Never Make a Mistake: Achieving Success in a World That Is Always Looking for Someone to Blame (2001). Major advertising campaigns represented in the collection include: American Tobacco Company (Bull Durham and Silva Thins cigarettes); Bristol-Myers Company; Bulova Corporation; Dr Pepper Co.; Food Fair/Pantry Pride; Hoover Company; Ladies' Home Journal; Martex; Pabst Brewing Company; Procter & Gamble; Pure Oil Company; and Joseph Schlitz Brewing Co. The collection also documents Sosna's role as supervisor of the Peace Corps advertising campaign in its first two years, from 1961 to 1963. Peace Corps materials include print advertisements; "Volunteer Radio Kits" distributed to broadcasters; one promotional film originally aired on American television; and a letter from Robert Sargent Shriver, Jr., first director of the Peace Corps.
2600 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Also, one phonograph recording in this collection is not immediately accessible, because it requires further processing before use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Sheldon B. Sosna Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts in 2003 and 2004.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1922 June 14 Born in Chicago
1942 Enlisted in the United States Army
1943-1946 Served three years in U.S. Army, Pacific Theater; achieved rank of Captain
1944 Married Relma B. Blevins
1946 Received MA from University of Chicago Received BA from Northwestern University (originally class of 1944, degree delayed by war)
1946-1948 Established sales firm, worked as manufacturers' sales representative Self-employed
1948-1953 Joined Gershuny Associates, a Chicago-based advertising firm, as Partner and Executive Vice-President; directed Gershuny's subsidiary companies DriJuice Corporation, Texto Products Corporation and Lewis & Clark Films
1953-1958 Joined the Leo Burnett Company as Senior Copywriter, promoted to Copy Supervisor. Supervised major accounts (Brown Shoe Company, Crane Plumbing, Hoover Company, Kellogg's, Pabst Beer, Pillsbury, Procter & Gamble, Pure Oil); worked as speechwriter for Mr. Burnett
1958-1960 Joined Grant Advertising, Chicago, as Creative Director. Supervised foreign operations and creative work within Grant's domestic offices, served as agency spokesman; supervised Grant's television production facilities in Chicago and Los Angeles, produced and directed several commercials (Archway Cookies, Comet Rice, Dr Pepper, Old Milwaukee Beer)
1960 Received American Television Festival Award for Best Commercial: Health and Beauty Aid (Bristol-Myers Ipana toothpaste commercial)
1960-1963 Joined Doherty, Clifford, Steers & Shenfield, a New York City advertising firm, as Vice-President and Creative Supervisor; responsible for Bristol-Myers account
1961-1963 Developed and supervised first two years of Peace Corps advertising and recruiting campaign
1963-1965 Joined Sullivan, Stauffer, Colwell & Bayles as Vice-President and Copy Supervisor; responsible for American Tobacco Company, Bache & Company Brokerage, Bulova accounts
1965-1968 Joined Norman, Craig & Kummel; served as Vice-President and Management Supervisor; responsible for American Tobacco Company, Hertz, Revlon accounts
1968-1971 Joined J.M. Mathes, Inc. as Executive Vice-President
1972 Became Vice President of Marketing for the supermarket chain Food Fair/Pantry Pride, based in Philadelphia
1978 Founder and President of The Sosna Company, consulting firm specializing in supermarket advertising and marketing; pioneered frozen food advertising for Keystone Foods
1979-1988 Contributed regular column to Grocery Marketing Magazine, Sosna on Advertising
1981-2000 Sponsored annual Supermarket Ad Expo at venues across the country Founder, editor, and publisher of monthly Supermarket Advertising Newsletter; established Sosna as a leading voice in the supermarket advertising industry
2000 Retired after over fifty years in advertising
2001 Published Dodge #9: How To Never Make a Mistake: Achieving Success in a World That Is Always Looking for Someone to Blame
Collection Overview
The Sheldon B. Sosna Papers span the years 1922 to 2001, with the bulk of the material dating from 1948 to 1991. The collection documents Sosna's long career as an advertising executive and consultant, and contains materials from a wide variety of formats, including correspondence, writings, printed material, advertisement proofs and clippings, sketches, scrapbooks, slides, negatives, and film. The collection primarily provides a record of advertising campaigns Sosna developed as a copy supervisor, creative director, and advertising executive at Gershuny Associates, Leo Burnett, Grant Advertising, Doherty Clifford Steers & Shenfield, Sullivan Stauffer Colwell & Bayles, Norman Craig & Kummel, and J.M. Mathes, from 1948 to 1973; the collection has limited material relating to the specific agencies for which he worked. In addition, the collection documents Sosna's later writings, lectures, and seminars as an independent consultant in retail and supermarket advertising from the 1970s through 2001, including a complete run of the Supermarket Advertising Newsletter (1981-2000) and a copy of his book Dodge #9: How to Never Make a Mistake: Achieving Success in a World That Is Always Looking for Someone to Blame (2001). Major advertising campaigns represented in the collection include: American Tobacco Company (Bull Durham and Silva Thins cigarettes); Bristol-Myers Company; Bulova Corporation; Dr Pepper Co.; Food Fair/Pantry Pride; Hoover Company; Ladies' Home Journal; Martex; Pabst Brewing Company; Procter & Gamble; Pure Oil Company; and Joseph Schlitz Brewing Co. The collection also documents Sosna's role as supervisor of the Peace Corps advertising campaign in its first two years, from 1961 to 1963. Peace Corps materials include print advertisements; Volunteer Radio Kits distributed to broadcasters; one promotional film originally aired on American television; and a letter from Robert Sargent Shriver, Jr., first director of the Peace Corps. The collection is organized into six series: Correspondence, Writings and Speeches, Printed Materials, Advertisements, Scrapbooks, and Visual Materials.
The Correspondence Series includes limited business correspondence, advertising strategy memoranda, and mailings and solicitations specifically related to Sosna's supermarket consulting. The Writings and Speeches Series includes scripts of lectures and seminars Sosna delivered on retail and supermarket advertising throughout the United States from 1983 to 1994, limited market and client reports, and an account of his work with President Kennedy and Robert Sargent Shriver, Jr. on an early promotional film for the Peace Corps. The Printed Materials Series includes Sosna's professional writings on advertising (including an installment of Sosna on Advertising, a long-standing column featured in Grocery Marketing Magazine); a copy of his 2001 book Dodge #9: How to Never Make a Mistake; client materials (letterhead, brochures, mailings, including Peace Corps promotional materials); conference programs; and magazines. Most notably, the series includes a complete set of the Supermarket Advertising Newsletter, a monthly serial which Sosna wrote, edited, and published from January 1981 through December 2000. The Advertisements Series includes original page proofs, newspaper and magazine clippings, and concept sketches for client advertisements, with an emphasis on consumer/home products, cigarette, beer, and apparel industries. The Scrapbooks Series includes six scrapbooks of advertisement clippings, original page proofs, client brochures, and catalog mailings, primarily documenting clients in women's apparel and consumer/home products. The Visual Materials Series includes over 700 seminar slides originally used in Sosna's presentations on supermarket advertising, a set of color negatives documenting the Pabst Red Beer advertising campaign, and the only existing copy of a promotional film for the Peace Corps which Sosna wrote, produced, and edited. Large-format materials (clippings, proofs, sketches) have been removed from their original series location and relocated to Oversize Materials locations.
Other materials related to this collection may be found in the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives: Competitive Advertisements Collection and the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives: Corporation Vertical Files. For materials specifically relating to the agencies Norman, Craig & Kummel and the Leo Burnett Company, consult the Robert S. Smith Papers and the Kensinger Jones Papers, respectively. For materials relevant to American Tobacco Company advertising, see the James Buchanan Duke Papers, the Benjamin Newton Duke Papers, and the John M. W. Hicks Papers. For materials on beer advertising for the Pabst Brewing Company and Schlitz Brewing Company, see the Howard Scott Papers. Materials relevant to Procter & Gamble Company advertising may be found in the D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles Advertisements, the D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles Archives, and the Wells Rich Greene, Inc. Records. Additionally, materials relating to Peace Corps advertising may be found in the David B. McCall Papers.
Advertising -- Beer -- United States; Slides (photographs); Advertising -- Brand name products -- United States; Advertising -- Cigarettes -- United States; Advertising -- Clothing and dress; Advertising -- History; Advertising executives -- United States; Groceries -- Marketing; Motion pictures (visual works); Sketches; Scrapbooks; Peace Corps (U.S.); Negatives (photographic); Pabst Brewing Company; Ladies' home journal; Pure Oil Company; Procter & Gamble Company; Sosna, Sheldon B.; Shriver, Sargent, 1915-; Sosna, Sheldon B.; American Tobacco Company; Bristol-Myers Company; Bulova Corporation; Dr Pepper Co; Food Fair Stores, Inc.; Hoover Company; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Jos. Schlitz Brewing Co.
- Correspondence Series, 1958-1964 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes limited business correspondence, mailings and solicitations related to Sosna's supermarket consulting, and one folder of Advertising strategy memoranda that Sosna distributed while Copy Supervisor at Sullivan, Stauffer, Colwell & Bayles and at Doherty, Clifford, Steers & Shenfield. Of particular interest is a 1963 letter from Robert Sargent Shriver, Jr., first director of the Peace Corps, thanking Don Clifford and his staff at Doherty, Clifford, Steers & Shenfield for their work on early Peace Corps advertising. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Advertising strategy memoranda, 1958-1964 and undated (Box 1)
  - Letters
    - Letter from Robert Sargent Shriver, Jr., 1963 July 15 (Box 1)
      [Appointed by President Kennedy, Shriver served as the first director of the Peace Corps from 1961-1966.]
    - Letter from Richard R. Uhl, undated (Box 1)
  - Mailings and solicitations
    - The Consumer Network, undated (Box 1)
    - Supermarket Advertising Newsletter, undated (Box 1)
- Writings and Speeches Series, circa 1965-1994 and undated, bulk 1983-1991
  Primarily contains scripts and other materials used for lectures and seminars Sosna delivered throughout the United States from 1983 to 1994, with an emphasis on supermarket advertising and marketing. Scripts primarily document presentations Sosna delivered as an independent consultant to supermarket/food retailers, specifically for meetings of the National Grocers Association, the Grocery Marketing Institute, at Food Marketing Institute conventions, at state grocery organization meetings (in California, Indiana, Oklahoma, New Hampshire, and Florida), and for the annual Supermarket Advertising Seminar which Sosna founded in 1983. Also includes limited market reports on specific retail industries and clients, including Pabst Red Beer. Of particular interest is one folder of Advertising notes and addenda, which documents Sosna's professional career and profiles his prominent clients of the 1950s and 1960s, most notably his work on an early promotional film for the Peace Corps and his meeting with President Kennedy and Robert Sargent Shriver, Jr. during the film's production. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Client/Market reports (Box 1)
    - Advertising notes and addenda, circa 1965 and undated (Box 1)
    - Air Step: In Search of a Brand Image report, undated (Box 1)
    - Cole Products Corporation: Cole-Spa brochure, undated (Box 1)
    - Pabst Red Dinner Beer
      - Pabst Red Dinner Beer report, undated (Box 1)
      - Red Beer Concept Research, 1967 May (Box 1)
  - Seminar/Lecture scripts
    - Advertising/Marketing strategy lecture notes, undated (Box 1)
    - Associated Wholesale Groceries seminar, 1991, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - FEDCO seminar: How Advertising Works to Make People Buy, 1991, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Indiana Food Retailers: Advertising seminar, undated (Box 1)
    - Indiana Retail Grocers Association: Advertising seminar, 1990 (Box 1)
    - NAGWA advertising meeting: The Future of Supermarket Advertising, 1987 (Box 1)
    - National Grocers Association
      - Advertising presentation, 1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Futures seminar, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Oklahoma Grocers, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Seminar slide notes - Misc., undated (Box 1)
    - Seminar for Store Owners
      - Notebook, 1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Scripts, 1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Supermarket Advertising and the Consumer, copresented by Sosna and Mona Doyle (President, The Consumer Network, Inc.), 1989 (Box 2)
    - Supermarket Ad Expo, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Supermarket Advertising Seminar
      - St. Louis seminar, undated (Box 2)
      - 1983 seminar
        - Agenda (Box 2)
        - Scripts, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Slide notes/notecards (Box 2)
      - 1984-1985 seminar, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Supermarket Retailer Forum: Popai meeting, Chicago, 1992 Oct. (Box 2)
- Printed Materials Series, circa 1944, 1952-2001 and undated, bulk 1981-2001
  Includes Sosna's professional writing on advertising, a copy of Sosna's book Dodge #9: How to Never Make a Mistake (2001), client materials (letterhead, mailings, brochures), conference programs, and a limited set of magazines from 1952. The bulk of the series is composed of a complete set of The Supermarket Advertising Newsletter, a monthly publication Sosna edited and published from 1981-2000, along with an incomplete subject index of the newsletter. Of particular note in the series are Peace Corps Radio Kits distributed to broadcasters in 1962-1963. The Volunteer Radio Kit for 1963 includes a phonograph record of public service announcements for the Peace Corps featuring the voice of sportscaster Bob Delaney. Also includes two comics that refer to the Peace Corps which appeared in the New York Post comic strip Pogo in 1962. Arranged alphabetically; complete set of Supermarket Advertising Newsletter arranged chronologically by month/year.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  [Technical Services staff need to produce a use copy of the phonograph record before its contents can be accessed. Please consult with Research Services staff before coming to use this series.]
  - Article: A cure for the copycat syndrome, in Sosna on Advertising column, Grocery Marketing Magazine, 1985 Mar. (Box 2)
  - Book: Dodge #9: How to Never Make a Mistake: Achieving Success in a World That Is Always Looking for Someone to Blame, 2001 (Box 2)
    [Book published in paperback by Hats Off Books, Tucson, Arizona.]
  - Client Materials
    - Abbell Hotels, undated (Box 2)
    - Dr Pepper: article in Printers' Ink, Hal Stebbins on copy column, 1959 Mar. (Box 2)
    - Intercontinental Industries, undated (Box 2)
    - Lewis & Clark, Inc.: letterhead, undated (Box 2)
    - Ochs Paper Company, undated (Box 2)
    - Pabst Brewing Company: How to ruin a hotel clerk's day [pamphlet], undated (Box 2)
    - Pantry Pride/Food Fair, 1974 and undated (Box 2)
    - Peace Corps
      - Comic Strip: Pogo, New York Post, 1962 (Box 2)
      - Peace Corps News, 1962 Jan. (Box 2)
      - Recruiting Radio Kit, 1962 (Box 2)
      - Volunteers Radio Kit, 1963 (Box 2)
        [Among other materials, includes record album entitled Peace Corps Volunteers/The Advertising Council Public Service Announcements.]
    - Specialjoy, Inc., undated (Box 2)
    - Spectoculars (Intermares Inc.), undated (Box 2)
    - J. Spencer & Company, undated (Box 2)
    - Staffin-Johns Mattresses, 1952 and undated (Box 2)
  - Conference Programs, 1983-1985, 1995-1997 (Box 2)
  - Magazines
    - Kiwanis Magazine, 1952 Apr. (Box 2)
    - Life Magazine Mailing Plan, undated (Box 2)
    - Newsweek, 1952 July 21 (Box 2)
    - V.F.W. Magazine, 1952 Apr. (Box 2)
  - Supermarket Advertising Newsletter, 1980-2000 (Box 3-4)
    - Inaugural Mailings, 1980-1981 (Box 3-4)
    - Subject Index, 1987 (Box 3-4)
    - Supermarket Advertising Newsletter, 1981 Jan.-2000 Dec. (monthly serial, complete set), 22 folders (Box 3-4)
- Advertisements Series, 1922, 1951-1973 and undated
  Divided into two groupings: Clippings and Proofs, and Sketches and Concepts. Includes original page proofs, newspaper and magazine clippings, and concept sketches for client advertisements, with an emphasis on the consumer/home products, cigarette, beer, and apparel industries. Key clients represented include American Tobacco Company (Bull Durham Cigarettes), Bristol-Myers, Bulova, Dr Pepper, Food Fair/Pantry Pride, Hoover, Ladies' Home Journal, Martex, Pabst Brewing Company, Procter & Gamble, and Pure Oil Company. Of particular interest is one folder of early Peace Corps advertisements Sosna developed while at Doherty, Clifford, Steers & Shenfield. Series also includes two uncredited cigarette advertisements [Bull Durham (1922) and Fatima (undated)] presumably intended as marketing research for Sosna's work in cigarette advertising, and one folder of Spanish language concept boards for beverage advertisements (uncredited and undated). Arranged alphabetically by client within each grouping.
  - Clippings and Proofs (Box 5)
    - Abbell Hotels (Stanley, Alexandria, Paramount, Willard, Summit), 1952-1953 and undated (Box 5)
    - Advertising Management Co., 1972 (Box 5)
    - Allstate Insurance, 1957 and undated (Box 5)
    - American Meat Institute, 1955 (Box 5)
    - American Tobacco Company
      - Bull Durham Cigarettes
        - Historical advertisement, 1922 (Box 5)
        - Proofs, 1967-1968 and undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Silva Thins, 1968-1969 and undated (Box 5)
    - Apparel Misc., 1953 and undated (Box 5)
    - Archway Cookies, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Bauer & Black
      - Bandages and first aid, 1953-1954 (Box 5)
      - Stockings, 1952-1954 (Box 5)
    - Better Vision Institute, 1961 and undated (Box 5)
    - Bike Athletic Supporters, 1954 (Box 5)
    - Bristol-Myers (Mum and Ipana), 1961-1962 and undated (Box 5)
    - Brown Shoe Company, undated (Box 5)
    - Bulova, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
    - Cole Products Corporation: Cole Spa Drink Dispenser, 1952-1953 and undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Comet Rice, undated (Box 5)
    - Crane Company (heating and utilities), 1955 and undated (Box 5)
    - Dormay Products, undated (Box 5)
    - Dr Pepper, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
      [Includes laminated advertisements and clipping from the groundbreaking FREE! Genuine Dr Pepper bottle cap campaign.]
    - DriJuice Corporation: InstaLemon, 1953 and undated (Box 5)
    - Emulsol Corporation, undated (Box 5)
    - Englander Beds, 1956 (Box 5)
    - Fabrico Manufacturing Corporation, undated (Box 5)
    - Food Fair/Pantry Pride, 1973 and undated (Box 5)
    - Grant Advertising, 1955, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Herbert-Levy (apparel), undated (Box 5)
    - Hoover Appliances, 1955-1957 and undated (Box 5)
    - International Harvester, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Ladies' Home Journal, 1960 (Box 5)
      [Includes advertisements featuring President Kennedy and Winston Churchill.]
    - Leo Burnett Advertising: Twentieth Anniversary commemorative broadside and advertisement, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Leo's Advance Theatrical Shoe Co., undated (Box 5)
    - Liggett & Myers Tobacco Co.: Fatima Cigarettes (historical advertisement), undated (Box 5)
    - Manhattan (sportswear and furnishings), 1963-1964 (Box 5)
    - Martex, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - Pabst Brewing Company
      - Old Tankard Ale, 1957 (Box 5)
      - Pabst Blue Ribbon
        - Newspaper advertisements - Various, 1956-1957 and undated (Box 5)
        - Pabst Blue Ribbon Touch campaign, 1956 and undated (Box 5)
        - Pabst is the name campaign, 1957 and undated (Box 5)
        - What'll You Have campaign, 1956 and undated (Box 5)
        - Various, 1956-1957 (Box 5)
    - Peace Corps, circa 1962-1963 (Box 5)
    - Procter & Gamble: Camay Soap, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Pure Oil Company, 1954, 1957 and undated (Box 5)
    - Schlitz Brewing Company: Old Milwaukee Beer, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Specialjoy, Inc., 1951-1952 and undated (Box 5)
    - Spectoculars (Intermares, Ltd.), undated (Box 5)
    - Staffin-Johns Mattress, undated (Box 5)
    - Tea Council, 1957 (Box 5)
    - U.S. Tobacco Company: Encore cigarettes, 1961 (Box 5)
  - Sketches and Concepts (Box 6)
    - American Tobacco Company: Half and Half cigarettes, undated (Box 6)
    - Appointment hosiery, undated (Box 6)
    - Bache & Co., undated (Box 6)
    - Bulova, 1964 (Box 6)
    - DriJuice Corporations: InstaLemon, 1953 (Box 6)
    - Martex: Lady Pepperell designs, undated (Box 6)
    - Pabst Brewing Company
      - Pabst Red, undated (Box 6)
      - What'll You Have advertisement, undated (Box 6)
    - Pure Oil Company, undated (Box 6)
    - Spanish language advertisements (Alvear, Philips, Schweppes), undated (Box 6)
    - Tennyson Menthol cigarettes, undated (Box 6)
- Scrapbooks Series, 1947-1971 and undated, bulk 1948-1958
  Contains six large scrapbooks of advertisement clippings, page proofs, client brochures and catalog mailings that primarily document Sosna's early advertising career, with a focus on women's apparel and consumer/home products. Arranged chronologically by scrapbook.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1947-1949 and undated (Box 7)